Marcia Ann Gillespie papers SSC.MS.00464
Sophia Smith Collection
Marcia Ann Gillespie papers
1987-2002
Sophia Smith Collection
Gillespie, Marcia Ann
SSC.MS.00464
23 linear feet (18 containers)
Marcia Anne Gillespie was Editor in Chief of both Essence Magazine and Ms. Magazine and served as President of Liberty Media for Women, Inc. Her papers include faxes; memoranda; correspondence; electronic mail; magazines, videotapes, and books; pamphlets; reprints of paper and internet articles; typescripts of essays submitted to Ms.; faxes and photocopies of correspondence to and from Gloria Steinem; contracts, correspondence and memoranda re: Gillespie's speaking engagements; photographs; travel documents; awards and commendations; memorabilia; agendas, minutes and printed matter from various organizations in which Ms. Magazine, as a corporate entity, or Gillespie, as its Executive Editor, took an interest.
Biographical Note
Marcia Anne Gillespie was born in Baldwin, New York on 10 July, 1944. She earned an A.B. in American Studies at Lake Forest College in 1966. Since 1971 she has lectured widely on college and university campuses and to women's groups, and has authored innumerable articles and essays. From 1971 to 1980, Gillespie was Editor in Chief of Essence Magazine, and from 1975 to 1980 was Vice President of Essence Communications, Inc. From 1980 to 1996, she served as an advisor to editors and publishers, providing creative solutions for publishing and editorial problems. From 1987 to 1990, and again in 1992, she was Executive Editor of Ms. Magazine, and in 1993 she was appointed Editor in Chief, which position she held until the Feminist Majority Foundation purchased the magazine in 2001. Gillespie also served as President of Liberty Media for Women, Inc., a limited liability corporation that, for a time, owned Ms. Magazine.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Related Materials
Ms. Magazine Records; Steinem Papers
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of files from the office of Gillespie's Ms. Magazine executive assistant, Cheryl Lynn Rogers, and includes faxes; memorandums; correspondence; electronic mail; magazines, videotapes and books pertaining to women, race, violence, population growth, family planning, and other topics; pamphlets; reprints of paper and internet articles; typescripts of essays submitted to Ms.; faxes and photocopies of correspondence to and from Gloria Steinem; contracts, correspondence and memoranda re: Gillespie's speaking engagements; photographs; travel documents; awards and commendations; memorabilia; agendas, minutes and printed matter from various organizations in which Ms. Magazine, as a corporate entity, or Gillespie, as its Executive Editor, took an interest; and issues of Ms. Magazine.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These papers were donated by Marcia A Gillespie on 2002-02-15.
African American women--Biography--Sources; African American women in the professions--History--Sources; Women editors--United States--Biography--Sources; Women journalists--United States--Biography; Agendas; Appointment books; Audiotapes; Awards; Electronic mail; Faxes; Itineraries; Computer media; Minutes; Publications; Research; Typescripts; Videotapes; Feminism--United States--History-Sources; Women's rights--History--20th century-Sources; press releases; Women's periodicals, American -- History -- Sources; articles; Writings; Photographs.; Books; memorabilia; Pamphlets; correspondence; clippings; Gillespie, Marcia Ann; Gillespie, Marcia Ann, 1944-; Steinem, Gloria; Ms.--History--Sources
- Series I. Files from office of Gillespie's executive assistant, 1987-2002
  - Faxes, 1999; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Unused Forms, 1999; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Staff Memorandums, 1999-2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Magazine Publishers of America Annual Report, 1998; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1998-2002; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Photos, 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Media Issues, 2000-2001; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Board Meeting, 2001; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Press Releases, 2001 October; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Electronic mail, 2001; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Ms. Magazine Events in California, 2001 September 10-11; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Planned Parenthood, 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Violence Policy Center, 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Newsletters Reproductive Justice, 2001; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Newsletters Women, 2001; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Newsletters Miscellaneous, 2001; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Submissions on Speculation, 2001; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Faxes and photocopies of correspondence to and from Gloria Steinem, 1999-2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Requests and Thank Yous for Speaking Engagements, 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Submissions, 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Reader Responses, 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - File re Ms., 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Solicitations, 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Greeting Cards, 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - NOW, 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Personal, 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Contributions, 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Arthur Ashe Institute, 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Gail Small - Native Action, 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 2000; 1 items (Box 1)
  - Business Cards, 2001; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Zip Disk: Ms. Magazine file #1, 2001; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Women of the Year Awards: correspondence and memorandums, 2000-2001; 1 items (Box 2)
  - General correspondence, 2000; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Ms. Magazine Editorial Expenses, 1998 January; 1 items (Box 2)
  - General correspondence, 1998; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Stephanie Hiller correspondence, 1998; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Robin Marantz Henig correspondence, 1998; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Girls Inc.: correspondence, pamphlets and brochures, 1995; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Johanna Garfield correspondence, 1998; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Global Fund for Women: correspondence, pamphlets and brochures, 1998; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Disgruntled Correspondence to Ms., 1994-1996; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Harlem Dowling-West Side Center for Children and Family Services, 1994; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Domestic violence: correspondence, electronic mail, faxes and reports, 1994-1996; 1 items (Box 2)
  - The Empower Program: correspondence and newsletters, 1996; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Educational Equity Concepts, Inc.: Correspondence, pamphlets, agendas, and memorandums, 1998; 1 items (Box 2)
  - File re Marcia Ann Gillespie's book, 1999; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Weekly Planner, 1997; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Ms. financial records, 1991-1997; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Ms. budget, 1994; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Ms. monthly report, 1995 April; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Ms. editorial expenses, 1997 September; 2 items (Box 2)
  - "Queries and proposals": Correspondence, pamphlets and brochures, 1998; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Lordly and Dame, Inc.: MAG speaking engagements: contracts, correspondence, and memorandums, 1993-1998; 1 items (Box 2)
  - Videotape: Glamour Women of the Year Tribute: Ruth Whitney Tribute, 1999; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Videotape: eWomen Network.com, 1999; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Ms. clippings about the 25th anniversary of the magazine, 1997 September; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Notes, 1997; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Readers responses to Ms., 1993; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Planned Parenthood, 1993; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1995-2001; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Speaking engagements, 1999; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Biographical material, 1997; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Heart Beats of Jamaica Fund Raiser, 2000 September; 1 items (Box 3)
  - American Assembly on "Racial Equality", 2000; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Krestyanka [Russian magazine], 2000; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Educational Equality Concepts, Inc., 2001; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Violence Policy Center, 2001; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Photos, 1995-2000; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Greeting Cards, 1999; 1 items (Box 3)
  - CD-Rom: Ms.: A Selection of songs from albums reviewed by Ms. Magazine, 2001; 1 items (Box 3)
  - Gillespie's awards, commendations and memorabilia, 1995-2001; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Feminist buttons, 2000; 1 items (Box 4)
  - 2 small, sealed Ms. boxes, event invitation ("We're Back! Politics/Faith/Facts 'n Face-lifts/Money/Power" etc.), 2000 Aprily 12; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Desk ornament: Women of the Year Award (to Ruth Bower), 2000; 1 items (Box 4)
  - 3.5x5 transparencies of Women of the Year Award desk ornaments, 2000; 1 items (Box 4)
  - General correspondence: Includes rejection letters for articles, speaking requests and other such mail, 1994-1995; 1 items (Box 5)
  - General correspondence: Includes rejection letters for articles, speaking requests and other such mail, 1995-1998; 1 items (Box 6)
  - Appointment books (computer-generated), 1995-1998; 1 items (Box 6)
  - Peggy Horan and Associates, 1999; 1 items (Box 6)
  - Public Relations for Ms. Magazine, 2000; 1 items (Box 6)
  - Lunch with Frances Cudjoe Waters, 1998 January 8; 1 items (Box 6)
  - Readers guidelines, 1998; 1 items (Box 6)
  - Writers guidelines, 1998; 1 items (Box 6)
  - Women's Environment and Development Organization, 2000; 1 items (Box 6)
  - Milbank, Tweed, Hadly and McCloy, 2000; 1 items (Box 6)
  - Y.W.C.A, 2000; 1 items (Box 6)
  - Women in films: correspondence, memorandums, catalogs, press releases, 1992-1993; 1 items (Box 7)
  - General correspondence, memorandums, faxes, 1993-1998; 1 items (Box 7)
  - Biographical material - resume, 1994; 1 items (Box 7)
  - Personal, 1996; 1 items (Box 7)
  - Royalty statements for The Darden Dilemma and typescript titled "Reasonable Doubt", 1996-1998; 1 items (Box 7)
  - Folio Awards, 1997 March 31; 1 items (Box 7)
  - Laura Flanders Flair Magazine, 1997; 1 items (Box 7)
  - Margot Diamond Luncheon, 1997 September 24; 1 items (Box 7)
  - Feminist Majority Foundation: correspondence and memorandums, 1995-1998; 1 items (Box 7)
  - Educational Equity Concepts, Inc.: correspondence, 1994-1997; memorandums, faxes, brochures, pamphlets, typescripts; 1 items (Box 7)
  - Emerge Women's Resource Guide, 1997; 1 items (Box 7)
  - Planned Parenthood: electronic mail, memorandums, minutes, publicity material, faxes, 2000-2001; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Violence Policy Center: correspondence, faxes, and memorandums, 1998; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Take Our Daughters to Work: Press releases and clippings, 1996; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Teenage rape: clippings and report, 1994-1995; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Questions posed during Toronto speaking engagement, 1994; 1 items (Box 8)
  - The Abortion Access Project: manual, 1996; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Rebecca B. Rumsey, 1999; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Lauren L. writing sample, 1998; 1 items (Box 8)
  - General correspondence, 1993-1997; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Unum Corp.: correspondence, memorandums and publicity material, 1997; material; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Women's Action Alliance: correspondence, memorandums, faxes, reports and press releases, 1995-1996; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Women's Bond Club: correspondence and newsletter, 1995; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Women's Coalition of St. Croix: correspondence, 1995; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Veteran Feminists of America, 1995; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Victim Services advisory board, 1997; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Ms. University Program: correspondence, 1997; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Correspondence and memorandums pertaining to various meetings and public engagements, 1993; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Essays submitted to Ms.: correspondence and typescripts, 1998; 1 items (Box 8)
  - Clippings, 1997; 1 items (Box 8)
  - General correspondence, 1993-1999; 1 items (Box 9)
  - Mills College: brochures and publicity material, 1998; 1 items (Box 9)
  - "Comp lists,": Complimentary Copies of Ms., 1997-1998; 1 items (Box 9)
  - Million Man March: correspondence, clippings and press releases, 1996; 1 items (Box 9)
  - PENCIL (Public Education Needs Civic Involvement in Learning), WILPF (Women International League for Peace and Freedom), Victims Assistance Services, The Women's Forum, The Women's Museum: correspondence, brochures and pamphlets, 1999; 1 items (Box 9)
  - "Crazy" File: correspondence, 1999; 1 items (Box 9)
  - Articles of Interest, 1999; 1 items (Box 9)
  - Global Fund For Women: pamphlets and brochures, 1999; 1 items (Box 9)
  - Laubach Literacy: memorandums and reports, 1999; 1 items (Box 9)
  - National Black Women's Health Project, National Writer's Union, NOW, Open Society Institute: correspondence and memorandums, 1999; NOW, Open; 1 items (Box 9)
  - Ms. public relations: correspondence, press releases, memorandums, clippings and magazines, 1999; 1 items (Box 10)
  - Ms. circulation: correspondence, reports, ads, 1999; 1 items (Box 10)
  - Invitations to speak: correspondence, memorandums, itineraries, reports and faxes, 1999-2000; 1 items (Box 10)
  - Articles on Ms. and Ms. staff, 1999; 1 items (Box 10)
  - Speaking engagements: correspondence, memorandums and faxes, 1999; 1 items (Box 10)
  - Notes from meetings about future of Ms., 1998; 1 items (Box 10)
  - Financial information (personal), 1999; 1 items (Box 10)
  - Correspondence from Ms. subscribers, 1999-2001; 1 items (Box 10)
  - Christmas cards to Gillespie, 1998-1999; 1 items (Box 10)
  - Planned Parenthood Cocktail Party, 1999 March 22; 1 items (Box 10)
  - Lordly and Dame, Inc.: speaking contracts, 1998; 1 items (Box 10)
  - Biography files about Gillespie: press releases, magazines, curriculum vitae, 1995; 1 items (Box 10)
  - Letters to the Editor, 1998-1999; 1 items (Box 10)
  - Correspondence: Cheryl Roger executive assistant, 2000; 1 items (Box 11)
  - Speaking engagements, public appearances, and submissions to Ms.: contracts correspondence, memorandums, faxes and itineraries, 1999-2001; 1 items (Box 11)
  - To do, 2000; 1 items (Box 11)
  - Patricia Smith: articles, 2000; 1 items (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous: Women Welcome Women World Wide, Parliamentarians for Global action, Children's Defense Fund, Center for Gender Equality, The Entrepreneurial Women's Conference, About-face, at Canyon Press, Oprah, and Ms. Foundation for Women: correspondence, magazines, reports, and brochures, 1999; 1 items (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Magazines, 1999; 1 items (Box 11)
  - Printouts of Gillespie's electronic mail (in loose-leaf binder), 1998 October-December; 1 items (Box 11)
  - Notebooks, 1998; 1 items (Box 11)
  - Appointment books, 1994; 1 items (Box 11)
  - Confidential, 1998 December 7; 1 items (Box 11)
  - Ms. circulation: memorandums and complaints from subscribers, 1994; 1 items (Box 12)
  - White House re: child tax credit, 1997; 1 items (Box 12)
  - Essays submitted to Ms. for possible publication, and related correspondence, 1993-1994; 1 items (Box 12)
  - Cartoons sent to Ms. (not used), 1997; 1 items (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, memorandums, publicity material, and reports on the following people and organizations, 1992-1998; 1 items (Box 12)
  - Catholics for Free Choice, Center for Women Policy Studies: Summit on Girls and Violence, Coalition of Silicone Survivors, National Council for Research on Women, etc., 1999; 1 items (Box 12)
  - Books Across Ghana, YWCA of Greater New York, Compliment Design, Inc., NOW Legal Defense and Education Fund, Mathews-Dickey Boys and Girls Club (St. Louis), National Network for Women in Prisons, etc., 1998; 1 items (Box 13)
  - Clippings, general correspondence, and memorandums on how to use ECHO computer systems, 1994-1997; 1 items (Box 13)
  - Special Ms. issue on abortion: mailing lists and memorandums, 1995 May-June; 1 items (Box 13)
  - Invitations, 1998; 1 items (Box 13)
  - Ms. mailing lists (general), 1997-1998; 1 items (Box 13)
  - Magazine Publishers of America, 1998; 1 items (Box 13)
  - Ms. Magazine/MacDonalds Communications corp. correspondence re: outstanding payments from previous owner, 1996; 1 items (Box 13)
  - Outstanding writer's fee's, 1996; 1 items (Box 13)
  - Ms. Foundation, 1998; 1 items (Box 13)
  - General and personal correspondence, 1993-1994; 1 items (Box 13)
  - Ms. editorial readership surveys, 1992-1993; 1 items (Box 14)
  - Ms. 20th anniversary: press releases and printed matter, 1992; 1 items (Box 14)
  - Clippings and press releases about Ms., 1998; 1 items (Box 14)
  - Suggestions from Gloria Steinem to Gillespie re: possible article topics, 1998; 1 items (Box 14)
  - Letters to the editor, 1998; 1 items (Box 14)
  - Thank you notes to Gillespie, 1995-1997; 1 items (Box 14)
  - Photographs of Gillespie, 1997; 1 items (Box 14)
  - 4 Ms. covers (encapsulated), 1999; 1 items (Box 14)
  - Women in Management brochure, Unum Life Insurance brochure, newspaper clipping, photos and negatives, 1987-1995 (Box 17)
  - Distinguished Black Women Award plaque - Marcia Ann Gillespie, 1996 (Box 18)
- Series II. Videotapes, 1993-2000
  - Wrestling With Alligators, 2000; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 15)
  - NARAL NY: One Question, 2000; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 15)
  - Angels From the Next Generation, 2000; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 15)
  - Kathy and Mo: The Dark Side, 2000; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 15)
  - Mustard Seed Communities, 2000; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 15)
  - "Mustard Seed Jamaica", 1998; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 15)
  - Making It, 1998; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 15)
  - A Room Full of Women, 1998; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 15)
  - National Urban League Conference, Plenary Session IV: "The Glass Ceiling Cracks: The Start of a New Legacy", 2000; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 15)
  - Magnetic disks, 1993-1998; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 15)
  - "BookTV Episode 1-03", 2000; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 16)
  - "BookTV Show #1", 2000; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 16)
  - "Futures of Women", 2000; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 16)
  - Today in Los Angeles: Ms. Magazine/Marcia Clark/Candace Gingrich, 1996; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 16)
  - Dateline: Flirting With Disaster, 1997 October 24; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 16)
  - Women's History Month: Marcia Ann Gillespie, 1996; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 16)
  - CNN & Company #361: International Fallout, 1997; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 16)
  - CBS Sunday Morning: "Ms. Magazine", 1995; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 16)
  - Dateline: "Marsha Gillespie/Ms. Magazine", 1997; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 16)
  - In Style: Marcia Gillespie: A Conversation, 1997; 1 items (Videotapes) (Box 16)